Guide to the Annabel Jane Wharton Papers, 1962-2008 and undated RL.11174
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Annabel Jane Wharton papers
1961-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wharton, Annabel Jane, 1944-
RL.11174
17 Linear Feet
Annabel Jane Wharton is the William B. Hamilton Professor of Art and Art History in Trinity College of Arts and Sciences at Duke University. Her initial area of research was Late Ancient and Byzantine art and culture. The collection contains photographs, notes, and travel ephemera from research trips she took to sites in Greece, Italy, Spain, Turkey, Syria, Jordan and other countries in West Asia. More recent research interests include the effects of modernity on ancient landscapes. Included in the collection are contains diaries kept by Wharton beginning in the late 1960s until 2008.
Arrangement
Arranged into series: Travel Binders, Diaries, Photographs and Negatives.
Biographical / Historical
Born July 30, 1944, Annabel Wharton is the William B. Hamilton Professor of Art History at Duke University. She received her undergraduate degree from the University of Wisconsin at Madison in 1966, her M.A. from the University of Chicago in 1969, and her Ph.D. from the University of London (UK) in 1975. She is the author of ten books, scores of academic articles, and has contributed sections to over a dozen books. She serves on the editorial board for The Journal of Medieval and Early Modern Studies. Her research interests include Early Christian & Byzantine Architecture, architectural history, medieval architecture, modern architecture, religious visual culture, and new technologies for visualizing historical materials.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Annabel Jane Wharton Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Collection Overview
The Annabel Jane Wharton Papers document the professional life of Annabel Jane Wharton, the William B. Hamilton Professor of Art and Art History in Trinity College of Arts and Sciences at Duke University. Her initial area of research was Late Ancient and Byzantine art, architecture, and culture. Later research interests include modern architecture and new technologies for visualizing historical materials. The collection contains photographs, notes, and travel ephemera from research trips she took to sites in Greece, Italy, Spain, Turkey, Syria, Jordan, and other proximal countries. The Travel Binders series contains research files created by Wharton on international and domestic trips. They are composed of photographs, negatives, handwritten and typed notes, and ephemera from sites visited. The Diaries series contains appointment books kept by Wharton beginning in the late 1960s until 2008. The diaries track Wharton’s travels, administrative and professorial duties at Duke, and her personal engagements. Included among the appointments and notes are drawings in Wharton’s precise, narrow hand. The Photographs and Negatives series contain black-and-white and color photographs and negatives taken by Wharton. Some of them reflect more research trips, while others are family snapshots. The photographs are arranged by location names provided by Wharton.
Art -- History -- Study and teaching; Diaries; Slides (photographs); Black-and-white negatives; Color negatives; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Travel Photography; History, Ancient; Color prints (photographs); Wharton, Annabel Jane, 1944-; Wharton, Annabel Jane, 1944-
- Travel Binders, 1984-2001; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Travel Binders contain research material including photographs, notes, architectural drawings and plans, travel documents, postcards, and ephemera created and collected by Wharton on trips to ancient sites in Europe, Asia, and the Middle East.
  Maps are from Wharton's travels, primarily from Italy, Greece, Spain, Portugal, and Eastern Europe. Included here are files with photographs and other working proofs from Wharton's book Building the Cold War, published in 2004 by the University of Chicago Press.
  - Cappadocia, 1987; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Israel, June 1989; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous from Israel, Tunisia, and France, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Tunisia and France, May 11-29, 1990; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - France and Germany, May 6-22, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Syria and Jordan, 1992; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Italy, May 18 - June 1, 1993 (Box 2)
  - England, June 1-13, 1994; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Brooklyn Museum, July 5, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Berlin, April 23-30, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Spain, June 15-29, 1996; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Italy, 1996; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Cairo, Istanbul, and Athens, November-December 1997 (Box 3)
  - London and Tel Aviv, April 18- May 12, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Italy, Fall 1998 (Box 3)
  - Los Angeles, June 30, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Northern Spain, May 4-18, 2000; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Building the Cold War files, 2000; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - London and Switzerland, May 11-24, 2001; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Maps, undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
- Diaries, 1962-2008; 2
  The diaries chronicle Wharton’s professional and personal activities from the late 1960s to 2008, including a truncated diary from 1962. The diaries record her research trips, administrative and professorial duties at Duke, and personal engagements. Alongside her engagements, Wharton included detailed pen-and-ink drawings and extemporaneous notes in her precise, minute hand.
  - Diaries, 1962-1980; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Diaries, 1980-1993; 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Diaries, 1993-2003; 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Diaries, 2003-2008; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Meeting with Chancellor, undated (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL-11146-CS-0001)
- Photographs and Negatives, 1971, 1988-1995 and undated; 3
  The Photographs series comprises black-and-white prints of snapshots Wharton took on research trips to Italy, Turkey, Spain, Greece, among other locations. These photographs were separated from those found in the Travel Binders series by Wharton.
  The family photographs files contain miscellaneous photographs of Wharton and her family from vacations, her children's youth, family holiday cards, graduations, and other family activities. Negatives files consist miscellaneous negatives from Wharton's photographs of research trips, personal and family snapshots.
  - Trebizond, undated (Box 10)
  - Parenzo, Porec, undated (Box 10)
  - Torcello, undated (Box 10)
  - Cappadocia - Peristrema Valley, Soganlidere, undated (Box 10)
  - Istanbul - Thrace, undated (Box 10)
  - Bulgaria/Yugoslavia, undated (Box 10)
  - Venice, San Marco, undated (Box 10)
  - Greece, Byzantine architecture, undated (Box 10)
  - Asia Minor, South and West, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Armenia and Georgia, undated (Box 10)
  - Rock-cut churches in Sicily, undated (Box 11)
  - Capitals - Monreal and Syracusf, Monreal - general views and plan, undated (Box 11)
  - Monuments, Sicily, undated (Box 11)
  - North Mesopotamia, undated (Box 11)
  - Cappadocia - built monuments, Belisirma and Sivrihisar, undated (Box 11)
  - Chapels - Soganli, Goreme, Cemil, undated (Box 11)
  - East Turkey, general, undated (Box 11)
  - Cappadocia - Avcilar, Cavusin, Cemil, Maurucan, Semile, Sovic, Urgup, Zilve, undated (Box 11)
  - Cappadocia, undated; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Jordan, Syria, undated; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Rome, Israel, Tunisia/France, France/Germany, Syria, Northern Italy, England, Home, 1988-1995 (Box 13)
  - Santiago, undated (Box 13)
  - Henesa (?), Bilbao, undated (Box 13)
  - Barcelona, undated (Box 13)
  - Lyon, undated (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous and oversize photographs, undated (Box 13)
  - Family photographs, undated (Box 13)
  - Family photographs, undated; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Family photographs, undated; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Negatives, undated; 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Negatives, undated; 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Slides, undated (Box 17)